<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written out of the countrey to a Parliament-man, in answer to a quære by him made, how the people generally stood inclined to the proceedings against the King, and the intended change of government</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12979497</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12979497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 719:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written out of the countrey to a Parliament-man, in answer to a quære by him made, how the people generally stood inclined to the proceedings against the King, and the intended change of government</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96164:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96164:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER Written out of the COUNTREY TO A PARLIAMENT-MAN, In ANSWER to a <hi>Quaere</hi> by him made, How the People generally ſtood in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to the proceedings againſt the KING, and the intended Change of <hi>GOVERNMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Yeer 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:96164:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96164:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppoſe, you have made choice of me to ſatisfie you in theſe great particulars, as a man who (having in the late diviſions of the Kingdom ſteered in ſo equall a way betwixt the King and Parliament) may be more willing and able impartially to diſcover the diſpoſition and inclination of all parties (and conſequently of the Kingdom in generall) then any other who hath appeared more concerned then my ſelf. You have moved a queſtion (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) wherein I conceive my ſelf bound to endeavour a ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not onely to your ſelf, but to the whole Houſe whereof you are a Member, and all others who plead the neceſſity of a change of Government; and if you ſtill think me worthy of the credit which you have heretofore given to my opinion in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I dare, without much arrogance, take upon me to give you as clear light herein, as moſt men can, having ever ſince the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Armies Remonſtrance, made it my buſineſſe to feel the pulſe (and from thence conjecture the temper of all men, with whom I could gain free diſcourſe, and that chiefly, becauſe the Army, in that Declaration, uſurpeth the name of the People of England.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to ſatisfie you, give me leave to undeceive you concerning the way of neutrality which I have hitherto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. I call God to witneſſe (before whom we muſt all, one day, give a juſt account of our actions) when the unhappy and fatall occaſions of diſcord betwixt the King and His two Houſes, were firſt (I determine not by whom) given, and thoſe by the fiery ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of ſome on both ſides ſoon kindled into a War, my duty and allegiance to my Prince, and my naturall love to my Countrey and it's liberty ſuſpended ſo the operation of my will, that like <hi>Buridan's</hi> Aſſe placed equediſtautly betwixt two bottles of Hay, my hunger carried me ſo ſtrongly to both, that I had not power to make choice of either: I was taught by the Word of God and Laws of the Realm, not to lift up my hand againſt my Soveraign
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96164:3"/>in any caſe, and it was equally imprinted in me by the Law of Nature, that I ought not to contribute to my own thraldome. Whether the Parliament had juſt grounds or not to ſuſpect any tyrannicall deſignes in the King; or whether jealouſies and fears were hereby pretended to engage the people in rebellion: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to remove the King from his evill Counſellors, ſignified, to take away his life, or His Majeſties withdrawing from the tumults of the City, was an offenſive warre upon the Parliament, it was not within my private cogniſance: both were pretended, and whileſt the truth of each was equally uncertain, I choſe rather to ſuffer the inſults, reproaches, and plunders of both parties, then to engage with either; as ſuppoſing patience the ſafeſt way for a Chriſtian, where action on either ſide might have involved me in treaſon to my Prince, or treachery to my Countrey. This was the true ground of my neutrality: and had the Parliament continued their ſolemn Proteſtations to God and man, wherein they aſſertained to us the integrity of their intentions; that they aymed at nothing but the glory of God, the purity of Religion, the greatneſſe of the King, the honour and freedome of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and happineſſe of the People, who was there amongſt us that did not bid you ride on proſperouſly? But ſince by ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, we find, that all this ſhew of holineſſe is put on to diſguiſe ſelf ends: that the glory of God is, as much as in you lyeth, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into ſhame, by intitling him to all your impieties, as ſo many acts of his Providence. Religion is profaned by every frantick brain that can pretend the Spirit; and inſtead of the purity of the Goſpel, you have revived all the exploded Hereſies of former Ages.</p>
            <p>As for the King let us behold his greatneſſe: it is almoſt three yeers ſince you have kept him cloſe priſoner, in which time (to ſatisfie the cry of the people) you have thrice entred into a Treaty of Peace with him, but intending ſurely nothing leſſe, for your Demands have ever been ſo unbecoming the duty and modeſtie of Subjects, as if your ſole ayme was to obtain a denyall, and then to lay the breach on his ſide; for when His Majeſtie hath been upon the point of condeſcending to all, you have thrice ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered (nay invited) inferiourperſons in the Army audaciouſly to ſnatch him from your Commiſſioners, and now are readie to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96164:3"/>his life to your great Idoll, for raiſing warre againſt his people: were you not once aſhamed to acknowledge that you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended any hurt to his Royall Perſon, when he was your Enemy in the Field, and can you now legally try him for the ſame thing? But the inſpired tell you, this muſt be done, leſt <hi>Samuel</hi> riſe up and reprove you, as he did <hi>Saul</hi> for ſparing the Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites. Is this the honour and freedome of Parliaments, to ſit and Vote the reſults of a Councell of Warre? to ſuffer your Members to be torn from the Houſe by your own Servants? It was the Kings great crime, which made you pretend the War lawfull on your ſide, and meerly defenſive, that He demanded five of your Members to Anſwer the Law for matters of high Treaſon, and ſhall five parts of ſix of the Houſe of Commons be baniſhed, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, or affrighted from thence, and a handfull of you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Seſſion, and call your ſelves a Parliament? if you can interpret the ſhaking of a Sword hilt, freedome of Vote, what freedome, liberty, or property, ſhall the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> expect, but ſuch as a licentious; uſurping Army ſhall afford them?</p>
            <p>I beleeve (Sir) by this time, you perceive what account you are likely to have from me, concerning the inclinations of the people; but if your ſuperſtition leadeth you to enquire farther in them, by way of Augury, as the <hi>Romanes</hi> did by inſpection, into the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails of their beaſts, it will be requiſite for you to clear 3. things, before you can gain their approbation (the neceſſity, the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and advantage of a change). The neceſſity of this change is urged by the Army which cannot pretend to be ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Government as the leaſt Corporation of <hi>England,</hi> and it is grounded upon the equity of bringing offendors to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, by thoſe who have not the legall power of a petty Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: The offence which calleth for juſtice, is leavying war againſt the Kingdom; now (not to queſtion the juriſdiction and power which are ſo ridiculouſly aſſumed) we enquire, if the Army are ſuch ſevere chaſtiſers of waging warre, why are they themſelves ſuch Enemies to Peace? This will be beſt cleared if we obſerve, how ſquint-eyed they are in all their actions. The Counties peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned ſo earneſtly, the laſt yeer, for a Perſonall Treaty, that the Army ſuſpected their kingdom almoſt at an end, and with ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe foreſaw, that they muſt return into their former condition;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96164:4"/>this made them look upon the Petitioners as their onely <hi>Enemies,</hi> and aſſault, and ſlay them accordingly which muſt either divert them from their deſires of Peace, or animate them to revenge, and ſo make them lawfull Enemies, either of which would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to their ends. So now that the Counties are forced to lay aſide their Petitions, and all men betake themſelves to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate groans, under the continuance of an unſettled Government, theſe plauſible pretenders to ſeverity againſt the occaſioners of War, will arraign the King and murder him, thereby to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate the diviſions of the three Kingdoms, and ſo continue all power in their own hands; which is all that I can perceive of the neceſſity of a change.</p>
            <p>As for the lawfulneſſe thereof, by your enquiry into the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the people, you ſeem to expect the deciſion of right from them, and the ſubject of your curioſity is unjuſt, and you appeal to an incompetent Judge; for the people joyntly taken have no power to determine matters of that nature; nor taken individually have they underſtanding: your <hi>quaere</hi> therefore is prepoſterous in matter and form; and you might have ſaved your ſelf and me a labour, if you had made your application to the proper Oracles (the Scripture, and the Laws) for informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I ſuppoſe then you deſire not herein to know what you ought to do, but what may carry applauſe (whether well or ill done) and ſo ſeek not to pleaſe God but men. Not to leave you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unſatisfied in this, I muſt tell you, that many Jeſuiticall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts have been made in this and all the neighbour Counties, firſt by falſe ſuggeſtions, and ſcandalous imputations to detract from the honour of the King, and repreſent him to the abuſed multitude unworthy of the Government, and then the hands of ſome vagabonds have been by the ſollicitation of factious Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, affixed to Petitions, and tendred at the publick Seſſions to be countenanced as the generall Act of the County. But although it be an error in Politicks to ſuppoſe, any appeal ought to be made to a people once ſubjected to government, I dare preſume, if any ſuch unjuſt way of tryall were practiſed in this part of the Kingdom, an hundred voices for one (if not awed by force) would appear for a peaceable ſettlement under our former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, rather then to embroyl the Kingdom in a perpetuall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96164:4"/>War, for the ſecret ambitious ends of ſome few particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nowiſe qualified nor authoriſed to make a change. As for your ſelf and the reſt of the Members now ſitting, whileſt you were two Houſes, and thoſe entire, the People, although general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unſatisfied with your proceedings, yet reverenced the name of Parliament, and therein was your ſecurity; but now that the Lords Houſe hath deſerted you (except ſome few inconſiderable perſons, notorious either for their puſillanimity, folly, or ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude) and the greateſt part of your own Members either baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, impriſoned, terrified, or prudently forbearing to receive the Law from their mercenaries, and bind the Kingdom with their Enthuſiaſmes, that an handfull of you ſhould ſit, and not onely call your ſelves a Parliament, but exclude the King, and Lords, and uſurp to your ſelves the legiſlative power, and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it properly your own, becauſe you have ſo Voted it, is a frenſy that I once thought, could not have entred within thoſe wais. Your arguments are, in brief, theſe; <hi>That You repreſent the People:</hi> and <hi>That all Power is originally in the People:</hi> and thence you raiſe your dangerous ſuperſtructures. The miſunderſtanding, or miſ-application at leaſt, of that vulgar and true ſaying, <hi>Salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli ſuprema lex,</hi> hath led you and others into error, from whence I am ſure, you have capacity enough to be reſcued. Know there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Populus</hi> fignifieth the whole State, that is, the King and Lords, as well as the common People. Now, as the word People fignifieth the whole body of the Common-wealth, the King is properly the ſole Repreſentative of the people, and all their power is placed in him; as to make War or Peace, to raiſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys for the maintenance of War, to execute the Laws, to treat with forraign Princes, and the like. The Members of Parliament are Repreſentatives of the People for particular matters, as to preſent new Laws to be made, or old to be repealed by the King, (which plainly ſheweth where the legiſlative Power reſideth) to repreſent the aggrievances of the people, or prefer their deſires, and in ſhort to appear for the people of the reſpective Counties and Corporations ſummoned by the King to conſult upon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of publick concernment. Theſe Counties and Corporations they have not that power which you pretend, (for that were to make the government Anarchicall under a Monarch) nor can
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96164:5"/>they derive more to you then themſelves have.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuppoſe the power were, as you pretend, in the People, it muſt be underſtood in the major part of the people, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the major part of the Repreſentatives: but with what colour of equity can an inferior number of factious men invite an Army, to ſeclude their fellow-Members, and in their abſence, not onely make Laws to binde the whole Kingdom, but alter the Government already eſtabliſhed, and referre us to the wandring expectation of ſome others to be revealed hereafter in a dream? It hath been the prudent care of our forefathers ſo to reſpect the proper end of Government, (which is <hi>The peace and ſafety of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>) as to make choice of Monarchy (the beſt of Governments, becauſe leaſt ſubject to diviſion and confuſion). Now becauſe there cannot be that form of Government found out, which (by reaſon of the inſeparable corruption of mans nature) is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to abuſe (and the abuſe of Regall power is tyranny) they have therefore, to ſecure their poſterity from the arbitrary power of Princes, erected that high Court of Parliament, which is ſo happily compoſed, that we are thereby protected from all exceſſe, for as the King cannot Enact or Repeal any Law without the conſent of the two Houſes (which preventeth all tyrannicall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts) ſo neither can the Houſes without the King (which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth us from Anarchy and confuſion): for if the legiſlative power were ſingly in either, it might be miſapplyed to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of the other, which would conſequently diſcompoſe the peaceable conſtitution of our Kingdom: ſo then if the Regall Power encroach upon our right, we have redreſſe by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in Parliament; But if you uſurp the ſupreme Power to your ſelves, and either you or your Army tyranniſe over us, from whom ſhall we expect relief?</p>
            <p>Which ſeadeth me to the next Conſideration of the advantage which can hereby accrew to the generality of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and wherein that can conſiſt, I confeſſe ingeniouſly I am not wiſe enough to underſtand. Our Religion ſhall either be impoſed at the will of the prevailing party, and conſequently be alterable with every variety of fortune, or elſe we ſhall be left every one to the latitude of his own conſcience, which will be apt to lean and by as toward ambition, luſt, and avarice, as by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96164:5"/>ſad experience of theſe times we are too well taught. Our Laws, (you ſay) ſhall be purged, and digeſted into a new Modell, but to what end, I diſcern not, unleſſe it be that our ancient Laws (as likewiſe our ancient Religion) are diametrically oppoſite to your uſurpations; for the ſame cauſe it is thought fit to deſtroy our flouriſhing Univerſities, to expoſe them to the Viſitation of illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate men, to root out thoſe hopefull Plants of Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Sciences; and in their places to nouriſh ſpirits of ignorance and faction; hereby you endeavour, as much as in you lyeth, to captivate the very underſtandings of us and our poſterity. This peece of Reformation you borrowed from <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> and <hi>Watt Tyler,</hi> whoſe wiſdom thought it not fit to ſuffer any pen and ink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn-men to live. Wherein then ſhall this change of Government appear beneficiall to us? is it, that you will have a greater care, of our protection? indeed <hi>Abſolon</hi> promiſed as fair, if he were king, and we are pretty well acquainted with your performances.</p>
            <p>But to clear the matter, we are not ignorant, That Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be maintained by the ſame means by which is acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; if then you uſurp it from the ſucceſſe of your Army, you muſt keep a conſtant Army on foot to defend your poſſeſſion, and then the benefit of the people is, in ſhort, no other then this, a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Impofition upon their eſtates, to maintain this Army, a laſting War with <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> who being not concluded by your Votes, will doubtleſſe ſubmit to their lawfull Prince: a defyance of all the power of Chriſtendom, which (as it was wont to unite, by <hi>Croyſades,</hi> againſt the <hi>Turke</hi>) will without doubt look upon you as the greater uſurpers, and the more dangerous diſturbers of all fundamentall Government, in as much as you make way to theſe your deſignes, by the height of Rebellion, Perjury, and forfeiture of Truſt; and finally an unavoidable danger to their perſons and eſtates if they reſiſt your aſſumed power, and a contracting to themſelves your guilt, and the puniſhment due to it in this world and the next, if they tamely ſubmit.</p>
            <p>But you preſume that the head City will be a leading caſe to the reſt of the Kingdom, yet this may poſſibly deceive you, for we cannot ſee why they ſhould ſo readily contribute Commiſſioners to ſit upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife of their Soveraign, and thereby perpetrate to the Kingdome an exhauſting Civil Warre, (whoſe change of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96164:6"/>fortune may by the tryall of one ſingle battell ſubject them to the implacable fury of a revengefull Succeſſor, who will puniſh their exemplary defection with fire and ſword) unleſſe they had ſome aſſurance given them of exemption from future disburſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or at leaſt the leading men a ſhare of the ſpoil; if they will act the coy Duck to betray the reſt of the Kingdom into ſlavery. Thus if we look upon their blindneſſe, we cannot think them fit for our example; or if upon their ſelf ends, we ſhall not truſt them. But you have the Law in your hands, you have an Army that hath wonit by the Sword, and ſhall inforce it. I will not beſtow the pains to ſhew you, how improper it is for a Kingdom to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due it ſelf, how ungodly it is for an Army (although compoſed of <hi>Saints</hi>) to plead victory over the power that raiſed them: how impoſſible it is to conquer thoſe that fought not againſt you: ſuch is my caſe, and I dare affirm the ſame of one half of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>If for all this you are not to be turned from your purpoſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, at leaſt, as rationall men, with what difficulties you are to encounter in the compaſſing of thoſe ends which you propoſe. Your firſt obſtacle is the Kings life, but over that you plead a right, becauſe a power; God hath given him into your hands, and your illuminations direct you to deſtroy him. Yet he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Saul</hi> into the hands of <hi>David:</hi> you know the reſt of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is it not poſſible that the ſpirit which thus familiarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeth with you, may be a ſpirit of revenge, a ſpirit of ambition, aſpirit of madneſſe? The ſafeſt way to try the ſpirit is by Gods Word; he never gave that Authority to the Iſraelites, his own people, with whom he converſed face to face: nay the hand that cut off, although a wicked King, never yet went unpuniſhed: and if an Angel from heaven ſhould teach a Doctrine contrary to the revealed Word, we are commanded to account him accurſed. If the impiety of the act deferre you not, yet as men who would ſeem to repreſent the Nation, be more tender of its honour; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the putting of the Q. of <hi>Seots</hi> to death in Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth's</hi> time, (although for Treaſon pretended againſt her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Perſon) layed the fouleſt ignominy upon this Nation that ever it ſuſtained (becauſe therein was violated the Law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons): but how ſhall we ſtink in the noſtrils of all the world, if
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96164:6"/>contrary to the direct precepts, manicipall, the nationall, the morall, and the Divine Law, we ſhall attempt ſuch a horrid and barbarous impiety? There is nothing, I ſuppoſe, doth more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate you into the gulf of deſperation, then that Machavillian rule of ſecuring your former ills from puniſhment by attempting greater; you think (as well you may) that you have offended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond forgiveneſſe: I eaſily grant, that your forfeitures have been great, but whether it is not more probable that His Majeſtie who (I am confident) hath made his peace with God (a principall ſtep whereunto is forgiveneſſe) ſhould pardon and forget your inſults paſt, then that the Prince (who is tyed in honour to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate a Fathers death) ſhould let you eſcape unpuniſhed, I leave to your own judgement.</p>
            <p>If your proſperity hath ſwelled you above all theſe reſpects, yet conſider, you muſt propoſe ſome way of engaging the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your Nation faſt to you, for forced obedience will deceive you. It is not probable that the Prince and His Alleys will ſit as idle ſpectators of theſe your extravagancies: that the Nobilitie of <hi>England</hi> will tamely ſuffer themſelves to be proſtituted to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, with the unqualified rable; or that the Commons will be fond of any new Majeſties under whom they can hope for no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of condition. From theſe you can have no other ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable ſecurity but by oath, which being impoſed by force and terror, will peradventure be obſerved as long as that force is over them; but whenſoever an Army ſhall appear in the behalf of the King and his poſterity, you will finde your ſelves deſerted, and all men return to their originall duty and engagements, and then you may be humbled to your former conditions, and periſh unpitied. Thus in obſervance of your command I have deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my minde freely; I hope you will make uſe of it to your good, and not to the prejudice of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull Friend.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
